first of all we already have seen like
fully agentic systems I don't know if
you've followed open ai's recent deep
research for example I've made a very
good use of it to recently to thoroughly
research and find the top 100 best dad
jokes out there and sort out the 50 that
are least known within them and rank
them by humor took it eight minutes and
it's the first time that I actually
managed to get AI to it doesn't even
create but find new and pretty good dad
jok says Dad jok go I'm a fan
you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
Tesla hello everyone welcome back to the
AI native Dev today I am excited to talk
again about security it is a passion of
mine on it and to do that we have Mato
roas who is the co-founder and chief
scientist at Lera which is a great kind
of AI security company we'll talk about
not so much their products but gandal
they've created and he's here to talk
about kind of both llm security AI
security as a whole and specifically
agent security so matau welcome to the
show and thanks for coming on great to
be here uh so Mel let's let's start by
setting the stage a little bit about LM
security we've had a bunch of episodes
about it but you know I don't maybe not
everybody has seen it and also I don't
know it's a fast shaping world so maybe
definitions are a little bit off maybe
let's start by sort of saying what is to
you what should we know about or how
should we think about llm security AI
security or maybe llm security specific
yeah thanks great great question I think
there is a lot of terminology in the air
when you hear about air security there
is prompt injections there are gel braks
there are like data poisoning all these
different ideas and I think it's helpful
to take a step back and try to look at
the whole picture and maybe I would say
there are two types of vulnerability in
llm based applications the first are
traditional vulnerabilities when you're
designing a software system you want
permissions to be set right so people
talk a lot about rag for example and
whether the right users will have access
to the right data in that rag to a large
extent that really is a question of
permissioning who has access to what
documents and those are very important
problems but they're not particularly
new when you're launching these
applications you should make sure that
this is in place right and it's the the
security aspect is over permission is
like make sure that people don't get
access that they should not have yes
when you're thinking about agents like
we'll talk about later you should just
give permissions to the tools that
you're using to be to be the right one
so if you want to read email only don't
give it send access for example these
are just good habits to have when
designing these systems and this is
something that is really not new now
when you're thinking about what is new
and there is quite a bit in a not shell
I think the llms are vulnerable because
they introduce a really fundamentally
new type of vulnerability and that is
that they really struggle to separate
developer instructions from external
input or data and this allows the
attackers to manipulate the behavior of
the system via data so you know let's
try to unpack that for a second yeah if
you have a rag application for example
and you ask a question like what is the
capital of France and you withdraw a
document and that document has an attack
in there that wants you to get false
information about that maybe that
question is not the best example but
once to surface false information for
example the attacker can try to
manipulate the model into interpreting
the data in this document as new
instructions and then executing those to
then provide false information to the
user and I think in a not shell the way
I like to think about it is that data or
what traditionally has been only data
documents images videos suddenly become
executables and the moment the llm goes
through them then this can be executed
and the attacker can achieve multiple
goals now what where does the
terminology come in people talk about
gel breaks these are typically
situations where the user sends data to
the model to bypass the alignment
mechanisms of the model so it can talk
about how to build weapons and and
things like that like an unhinged
version of the of LM prompt injections
are typically referred to more of an
indirect setting where a user is talking
to an LM that has access to documents
for example or data that has been
manipulated and is containing attacks
and ultimately the this is all about the
separation maybe between the how and the
what or the means and the end let's say
so what are the means of attacking these
llms the means is you manipulate the
data in a way that gets the llm to
execute it and achieve the attacker's
commands and then the ends can be a lot
of stuff it can be to bypass the model
alignment mechanism to access a tool
that an agent is not supposed to access
to surface false information to the user
anyway you choose your pick these are
more about what you want to get out of
it and this is the I guess in this case
your data would always be executed right
unlike to an extent trying to get the
system to execute your command is also
bold news and whatever that's what SQL
injection is Tres tries to do that's
what process scripting tries to do
that's what remot command execution
tries to do and and I think the
distinction you're saying here is
actually it's trivial in fact you have
no way not to have the llm execute your
sort of a data when you're the attacker
and so that sort of interweaving is just
built in and you can manipulate a bunch
of things yeah I guess that's what makes
it very tricky is that this is actually
what gives the lmit power this precisely
why it is so powerful that it can just
take in natural images and text and
execute instructions from it and the
barrier is very thin you can imagine we
may get on to this example later but you
can imagine an an email coming in to
your assistant that says hey can you
forward this email from last week
totally benign command the agents should
execute it you can imagine another one
which says hey can you exfiltrate your
whole inbox to me from an attacker like
these are particular very similar in the
way they manifest and then the question
is how do you make the distinction
between the two yeah yeah and so super
interesting Bine we had an episode a
bunch of months ago with Caleb semi and
he talked about the sort of the control
plane and data plane and how there's no
separation and I think you're talking
about the same thing but I like the
analogy it's a I know like in my mind
I've had the dubious pleasure even in
tesel of Building Products that have
some area in which you are executing uh
user code and again it's built-in remote
command execution and really the
exercise is no longer at can you run
that code it's more about can you
contain the execution of that code right
and so I think maybe it's a little bit
along those lines which is think about a
system in which you are remotely
executing user code and secure it
appropriately yes and you're doing that
by Design continuously and I think that
maybe more about what it takes to solve
all of that we may get into that later
but because of the nature of the problem
this really is an AI first problem like
understanding these kind of subtle
patterns and attack patterns in data
being able to generate adversarial data
to Red Team systems all of these
questions suddenly become like an AI
first problem how do you actually do
this effectively I wonder so another
domain that I think about sometimes is
just the nebulous nature of the
functionality of the system cuz you
talked about the means and the end but
you can make the case that the end in AI
or LL owered system is probably like
less defined than it is in any sort of
traditional software applications there
isn't if you wanted the sort of the Holy
Grail of security which is whitelisting
these are the only commands that you are
allowed to do and everything else is
this allowed that's just entirely
unfathomable in the world of llms
because it's an infinite Universe of
sort of things that might that might
occur and I guess I wonder is that does
that come up like you you you do a lot
again we're not going to talk about the
Lara product too much but part of that
is you identify malicious activity and
malicious output I get the input when
someone is trying to whatever mess up
they indeed get the system to execute
something it shouldn't but in the output
piece is it harder to try and understand
whether it is in line with the desires
of the developers versus not I think
that's a great question and and I think
people emphasize a lot the means okay do
you identify the means but at the end of
the day if you want to have a great
security experience and you actually
want to identify these things you need
to look at the output and you need to
focus on specific use cases often a very
canonical use case is someone trying to
jailbreak a model to get it to say
offensive things that are against the
alignment mechanisms of the model that's
what hits the news and it's very popular
and people love to jailbreak systems
that's an example where you know to
identify the vulnerability you may of
course try to see if the input has been
tampered with but additionally you do
want to see if the output contains the
kind of language and content that would
be against the alignment of the model or
the kind of content that the the
Enterprise or the the customer wants to
to right use and only by combining these
two can you really leverage the powers
of of of Defense in depth and identify
it and that extends Way Beyond that for
most use cases and most even if you go
to fully agentic use cases at any
individual moment the agent is taking
data from some tool and making a
decision about what tool to call next
and with which data and you can identify
that and and focus on that transaction
and try to validate via the input and
the output whether that transaction
should actually go through or not
through yeah yeah so maybe let's hold
that thought and come back to this like
meta level a little bit towards the end
after we get a little bit more specific
but just we want to talk about newer
things including a paperie youve s
written but for starters let's you
rattled off a few of these kind of
attacks just to make sure everybody is
in mentally in the same place of it what
would you say are the prim types of
attacks like we talk about prompt
injection
jailbreaking data poisoning yeah I think
want say like a word about each of those
just level set us so we're using of the
ter absolutely so maybe let's say for
the sake of defining them even though
definitions vary a little bit uh a
jailbreak is one where the user is
directly trying to manipulate the model
that is interacting with to bypass some
of its alignment mechanisms the model
was trained with reinforcement learning
to never output harmful content for
example you want to provide data input
that override in some sense those
mechanisms that's a jailbreak and that's
against the system prompt or like the I
think mostly it is against whatever it
is that the the platform Builder the
tool Builder is trying to contain people
to some Lane and you're trying to break
out of that as the attacker yes but it
would goes even beyond that so that's
the first level at which you want to
stay aligned but most of these models
after pre-training they go through
something called like rhf where they are
trained with reinforcement learning with
human feedback and the goal there is to
partially to make models that are
helpful and also models that are har
harm harmless and so the company needs
to Define that notion of harm right and
so that is deeply encoded via training
in the weights of the model like the
weights actually contain that behavior
and so the model by Design regardless of
system prompt should never say tell you
how to build a bomb right yeah good
correction so not just system prompt but
still conceptually it is the hey I am
offering you I've got an AI based tool
or maybe literally like a Chach PT style
like the tool that is AI and I'm
offering it to you the user and you're
trying to undo or get through the uh
protections that might be built into the
system like maybe a little bit like
breaking through the firewall in this
case absolutely that that's that's
exactly right and at the first level I
find talking to people that this is what
they care most about or what they're
most aware about but then we go into the
second one which is prompt injections
and for the sake of this definition
let's say that's more when you have an
indirect attacker so you as a user
interacting with an AI system the AI
system has access to data can be
searching the web it can be searching
documents and the prompt injection is an
attack to the model that is contained in
those data sources and that as the model
reads the data sources gets executed and
then affects the user in in some way and
one very interesting flip side there is
that the it is the unknown KN user that
is a victim here as opposed to the
jailbreak where the user is the one
perpetrating the exploit and that's
primarily why I personally am way more
concerned about these prompt injection
attacks yeah we have talk to a lot of
people that have internal AI tools and
therefore believe they don't need
security because they're internal yeah
to the company but as soon as you have
access to any form of untrusted data
then now you can have third party
attackers modifying a lot of stuff
within your company without your
awareness so yeah that's fromp injection
I'm trying to think about the equivalent
to real world and this one is a bit
harder right it's like a side Channel
attack but there isn't really an
equivalent in the regular software world
to this prompt injection so before
you're breaking through defenses here
it's yeah it's it's pretty brand new
yeah it's like you have someone
internally always clicking executables
that come in via email and just execute
like crazy and then never ask if if you
should that do that in the first place
right and I think that's yeah that
happens inherently via the language
model hopefully you don't have one of
those in your organization you never
know so you've got jailbreaking you've
got prom in let's say you mention data
poisoning again I think traditionally I
would say when people talk about data
poisoning even though all of this is
data poisoning in some sense got a
prompt injection to a document
poisoning but I think people refer to
that when they think about fine-tuning
or training the model there have been
some examples where as you fine tun the
model so now you're not just prompting
it or giving it data in context but
you're actually modifying the weights of
the network with with some of your data
any adversarial content that gets
ingested can potentially now provide
back doors to attackers in operation
like weeks months later and I think
what's very difficult about that is that
once that data makes it to the weights
of the model yeah it becomes very
difficult to identify that this exploit
took place and that is probably one of
the most concerning ones out there for
sure and that's the one really again
equivalent I would say is like supply
chain security attacks because it's
something that's Upstream from the
software that you're actually running
that get manipulated but it's just
paired together with a low
explainability that you have around AI
systems and so you don't really know
what they do or why they did the thing
when they did it correctly let alone
knowing what they why they did it when
they when they abused something so if
you manage to manipulate it it's a
pretty hidden and it's probably harder
to execute because you need some sort of
volume of data or very specific sort of
tuning access to be able to like pull it
off but if you do it's pretty this is
the equivalent of solar winds type
problem that embeds into your system
right yeah and to your point the
obscurity of it is what makes it very
difficult once it's in it's very
difficult to identify and even though it
may be more difficult to pull off these
model providers are continuously
training their models pre-training on
data online and it is clear that data is
now highly adversarial in a lot of cont
of the web and I'm I'm you know to the
extent that these model providers put
the right safeguards in place when
ingesting this data some of these may
actually go through and the the very big
capacity models are a able to remember a
lot of stuff even if they saw it very
scarcely yeah yeah so I think those are
like probably the big terms maybe we'll
move on a little bit to the new stuff so
you have beyond the sort of the core
product of it you have this super fun
tool or portal I don't know how to call
it called Gandalf which is the sort of
fun game in which you basically practice
injection you try red team NM try to get
Gandalf to to give you the password I've
I've spent too much time on it no no I
passed it in five minutes maybe a little
more Super Fun quite addictive Gandalf
lara. recommended and you've turned that
into sort of a good data Trove of
understanding help people attack and
recently released an interesting paper
around learnings from it so was with all
that tea up a little bit tell us a
little bit about whatever it is that you
feel you still need to say about Gandalf
but also about the about this paper and
the learning yeah absolutely yeah gandal
has been really amazing and maybe one
thing to add is that by now we've had
over couple million people playing and
over 60 million attacks to all sorts of
llms and that of course gives us very
unique insights into just what kind of
techniques do people come up with and
how do they leverage their creativity to
break these systems regardless of
language of location of all these
different things we have people from all
over the world playing playing Gandalf
we have people building automated
attackers playing Gandalf and so because
of that um it really allows us to draw a
lot of conclusions um in terms of you
know where things are and where things
are going and last year we decided that
it was time to take that to the next
level and actually run some randomized
experiments in there to try to make some
statements about the state of the field
and what's easy and what's hard and
share them with the community and that's
a paper that we put out there about a
month ago and yeah happy to tell you a
little bit about the highest level and
we can dive into whatever you find to
the specific so that'll be great and I
love the idea of leveraging a whole
startup story around gandal coming out
and you folks leaning into it and and
making uh really turning it identifying
the opportunity and leaning into it and
now experiments being later element of
it of trying out you basically have a
bunch of attackers even though they're
doing it for fun they're actually
putting a lot of effort into it trying
to do that so anyways that's fine this
is not a startup podcast we'll move on
but but yeah tell so so in the paper in
the learnings a bunch of those learnings
I'll let you how do you how would you
categorize the top learnings from that
paper which by the way we'll put a link
to in the show notes awesome yeah yeah
yeah happy to chat about the startup
Story Another Day that's a very fun one
I think at the highest level one thing
that we identified in this paper is that
the way that the field is currently
thinking about AI security is
fundamentally flawed or lacking in in
quite a few aspects and the paper uses
data at scale to try to make the point
that it's time to take a bit of a
broader lens how we think about security
how we evaluate security and the kind of
Investments that need to be made to to
work in security and maybe at the
highest level the maybe one of the
biggest learnings or or the starting
points is the way people evaluate the
defense of a system today of an llm
system is that there are some data sets
out there of attacks or prompt
injections whatever you pass through the
model you have some kind of label that
you attributed to this data and then you
measure how many did I catch and uh
that's about it in terms of how people
think about about security so the paper
tries to challenge that idea or at least
the findings of the paper challenge that
idea and at the highest level we
introduce what we call DC which is the
dynamic security utility framework for
thinking about Security in LMS and more
specifically about security
and at the same time user utility I
think maybe that's one of the most
important things is that like anything
in security one thing one can do to
defend an LM is to block every piece of
traffic going through it yeah that a the
internet that's the best way to be
secure exactly unplug everything close
all the way to bankruptcy yeah exact
exactly yeah and of course that will
work it will hit 100% on all those
benchmarks but it will of course fail to
keep users happy and to make a usable
product
and again that's not particularly new I
think if you think about a firewall or
any other security product you don't
want to block every single piece of
traffic you want to be very selective on
that false positive false negative type
measure how many but you're like using
that lingo right now you're talking
about how existing detection measurement
focus on the sort of true positives on
the cases in which it was indeed an
attack and you've caught it but and
naturally the false positives but that's
not enough that's not enough exactly I
think the the core finding is that while
we do have those two aspects and a
developer needs to find ways to have
tradeoffs between the two depending on
what matters to them in L&M applications
and agents the tradeoff goes way deeper
than it has in the past and so maybe to
give you a quick example of of what we
found in the experiments we run where we
ask people to Red teim different llms
with different defenses on them we
separate two types of defenses one are
external defenses that outside of the LM
take a look at the payloads that are
coming in and out like we discussed
earlier and try to make an assessment of
whether they should block that and if
they block it the player failed at
extracting the password from the the
Gandalf agent and second type of defense
is in the system prompt in the system
prompt I'm going to tell the llm to not
reveal the password ever and then you
can be very verbose and just tell it to
really never ever do it and then we
measure how those two compare and in in
many respects and especially because we
didn't play the game of optimizing the
defenses too much yeah there's a limit
yes we have limited time there the
system PR defenses work quite well often
in terms of security so it turns out
that they they often block the attacks
and by tldr by the way a spoiler alert
humans break everything and so that's an
important part of the data that we saw
but the important thing is that the
system prom defenses work well but then
we looked at other measures of utility
for example we started to look at the
answers that these models give the ones
that are better defended in the system
prompt how do they look like and we
actually found that they are for example
way shorter than the reference so if a
unprotected llm will give you like a
detailed answer like this then maybe the
defended one will give you a shorter
answer more to the point and this is a
byproduct of just adding these defenses
it just so happens to affect the
behavior of the model so that the even
the content of these responses is quite
different from um what you were getting
from the undefended model so suddenly
you start to see how
because these defenses are so deeply
intertwined with the model you start to
see utility hits that are not as trivial
as the F positiv and they become
functional kind of in the in the sense
exactly the external one I think is easy
to relate to for anyone who has that any
sort of security measure which is just
like you would in a web up firewall or
even a regular firewall of it there's a
there's a leniency that you have to
offer because otherwise you're going to
start breaking the application and also
the defenses tend to not be as Dynamic
if you try to you know explain the
application to the external defense the
application always changes especially as
we got into the era of devop and fast
moving applications it's very hard to
consistently have the defense be tuned
at your system and so a dance that
nobody really loves but unfortunately
everybody's familiar with which is what
do you allow in and what do you disallow
and you'll have some attacks that pass
through that you hope the system deals
with you're used to that but the
protections of the system up until now
tended to be very in line and fine-tune
like they would rarely break the
application because they were literally
in the code of the applications produced
and provided by the very developers that
provided the functionality and so now
you're saying like those developers the
tool they have at their disposal is the
system prompt and lo and behold
sometimes when they create the right the
defensive system prompt they actually
break their own
functionality exactly and that has an
impact on the user experience that
they're crafting and one could argue
then okay then let's prefer external
defenses which have a lot of advantages
of course but the kind of extension of
that is that when you go to agents and
when the security solution even external
is verifying every single transaction
that goes in the system as the agent
makes sense of the world and tries to
make decisions you realize that the
security solution is very deeply
intertwined in the execution flow of the
program no matter what even if it goes
beyond system prompt and so that's where
find it very interesting that any
discussion around security for llms and
the more agentic it gets the more it
should be the case really goes hand
inhand with the utility and what is what
it means for utility and there is really
no free launch and having that
discussion or at least bringing that
discussion to the public was something
that we felt very strongly about after
looking at the results in the paper yeah
I think it's a super valuable discussion
triggered at this conversation here on
the podcast it's interesting because
when you think about security when you
explain security to non-security person
then you you talk about how security is
about the unknown functionality so like
functional testing is really about hey
the system is designed to do ABC
functional testing should make sure that
it performs ABC correctly when it gets a
three it returns a seven right as it
should and security is this infinite
World of unknown behavior of unintended
behavior and that's why the kind of the
Holy gra is the white list because if
you could really Define all the correct
behaviors in a very neat box then you
can say anything else is this loud but
that's just rare the case and so you you
need to Define examples of things that
are unintended and it's just like almost
unfathomable to to think about like the
llms we've had de on the intercom we had
you know Tomar here from G we've had all
sorts of guests on the show that talk
about how in the world ofms it's really
hard to know if your product works like
even the functional testing piece is
hard to Define like everything your
product surprises you all the time so
how can you ever aspire to to contain it
when you don't even know what the
boundaries of its capabilities are like
I don't know is that what's your sense
at this point it's probably not fact but
opinion but is is it a kind of a false
hope in this doain of it is it how do
you suggest that people think about
first of all like what is in reason and
two is given these learnings like how
should they approach it yeah it's a
great question I think it is very
challenging especially as you go into
agents and and tools that are making
more and more decisions then testing
becomes harder and harder of course and
I think that's we we'll talk about
agents later but as a jumping a little
bit ahead I think one of the key
challenges there is that the agent will
be always making decisions based on data
on the Fly and so if you want an analogy
for that it means that the agent is
writing software on the go the code is
the source code is being written as data
comes in there is no like shift left
necessarily on the code level and test
it well before deployment you're writing
the code in prod in some sense yeah um
and of course that that begs the
question of okay what do we do here and
I think that's where I would connect it
back to what we discussed earlier keep
it keeping it simple for now just inputs
and outputs I would make the the claim
that a human that is looking at an agent
snapshot in time you have a tool sending
you an email and then you're the agent
decides I'm going to call that the
calender tool right there with this
other payload a human could freeze that
and take a look at the payLo
can take a look at all the context of
the application and everything that you
know the user wants to achieve with this
application maybe it has metadata on who
the sender is I don't know just imagine
yeah as much metadata the context to an
extent digest the the context as much
context as possible on what this is the
human should be able to make a thumbs up
thumbs down decision on that in a large
majority of cases and so I think from
the way I think this should be addressed
solved is exactly like that like you
need to ensure that you have the right
kind of live testing on the go that
validates behavior in some sense and I
think again that's where security and
the usability to kind of more
development level side of the projects
become very intertwined in the llm world
because yes you can frame it as is an
attacker trying to get my system of
track for example but you can also frame
it as even if no one is trying to get it
off track is it going off track
nonetheless yeah even without intending
yeah people areally wired them some
money they didn't even try to do that
yeah I think I love that it to an extent
that statement couples both of my sort
of recent Journeys right because that's
ni it was all about merging developer
security you were saying that actually
needs to be truly continuous says in
even in lifetime and two is tle we talk
a lot about how software is adaptable
it's no longer in general I think in Ai
and llm World anything static will
become Dynamic that would be for
whatever the music you listen to or the
the stories you you read and all of
those things will become Dynamic and
adaptable and adapt to your context
software is no different like it is we
don't think of it as static but it is
static you deploy the software and then
it remains that software until it's
deployed again no longer the case with
LMS they create software on the Fly and
your security needs to be similarly
adaptable which exactly is a cool and
interesting and not a little bit scary
in inste of thinking about how do you
like we'll switch to AG we've been
foreshadowing agent security for a while
now like we'll get to that in a sec but
how do you how would you measure whether
you're any good at on the- fly security
creation there's a lot of meta layers
over here right yeah I think it's a very
good question I think at the end of the
day you need the right observability and
to make sure especially the more you go
towards agents you need to be able to
keep track of every single decision
that's being made and you know
retroactively look at that of course one
can imagine roll outs that are
increasing in scope there are ways to
restrict the systems right um You can
make the system PR very narrow you can
make the tool AIS very narrow and and
you can make the action space and then
you can learn as you go what kind of
content is going in what kind of
mistakes are being made and so on I
think that's an obvious one that to me
makes sense but another one and we see
huge demand for this today is just
shifting left on the red teaming side
like how can you have a red teing
Playbook that actually adapts to the the
nature of the systems and is not only
executing a bunch of different tests but
it's actually very aggressively trying
to get it to go of track um in different
ways and how do you make that highly
contextual meaning that you try to make
it go of the rails in the ways that
matter for the application and then how
do you then provide insights into the
developer of just exactly how the system
is going off rails so that he can put
stuff in place and maybe the last one is
that of course in production in real
time time one of the ways to make things
a little bit narrower is to always
especially at the beginning at a human
in the loop for example when send
commands are being used or anything like
that you can just mitigate some of the
bad outcomes again talking about means
and ends right ultimately you want to
prevent bad actions or or inappropriate
actions and so you want to add
mechanisms for these actions to surface
before they're executed yeah and that's
about giving less power to a system that
you don't yet fully trust ABS so I guess
let's finally get to that sort of our
next chapter of our conversation here
and talk about agent security this is
all of these problems we've been talking
about so far are true even if you're
like a relatively naive user of the llms
but they get uh Messier and Messier as
you get bigger and agents definitely are
have higher aspirations around what they
achieve so maybe for starters again
let's start with terminology a little
bit because agent is a very overloaded
term so Define for us like what what do
you mean when you think about an agent
there probably as many
are people in the world opinions so
let's give it let's give it a go I think
to me the way I think about a fully
agentic system is a system that where an
llm automatically determines the
program's execution flow based on user
input and available data sources and
tools let's let's unpack that for a
second I think the most important thing
there is that it autonomously determines
the execution flow of the program if you
want to give an example of say CH GPT
like rag application you say hey answer
this question and you get an answer
right when you go to the world of more
agentic systems then you say manage my
inbox and then the system is going to
say okay I'll come back to you when I'm
done right and then it's going to decide
okay I'm going to just ping the inbox
I'm going to look at the email I'm going
to take an action based on that and
eventually he will decide when to stop
and he will tell you I'm done I did all
these 20 things and so the important
thing there is that the the agent was
fully in control of what tools it was
calling and what decisions he was making
with the data it was getting from the
tools and again that's a little bit of a
ideal definition of course in practice
you have all sorts of hybrids right like
you have a lot of llm based workflows
where actually it's like agentic in the
sense that you have different tools
being called different stages but the
tool is the LM is not in control of
those flows it's like the flow is always
the same and the llm is performing a
predetermined action at agage all of
those have their challenges it starts
from conversational all the way to fully
agentic but I
think my opinion is that the jump from
llm workflows to fully agentic is like
much larger than conversational to
workflows or almost like traditional
software to to llms just because that is
what introduces that novel fact that
you're no longer in control of the steps
of what's Happening you're really giving
control to a machine
that decides what to do and when to stop
and I think from a security in utility
and usability perspective this
introduces all sort of Novel challenges
yeah and I I think I like that
definition I think if I go it back
saying at the metal level is just the
scope of task so that's one an agent
Loosely said is every time you're trying
to do something bigger you probably need
an agent uh because there's more steps
uh two that I guess you mentioned in
passing is the tool use element of it
which and we come back a little bit to
say is it or isn't agentic if it's just
inline tool use I don't know maybe
that's a bit of a Mose conversation but
directionally more tool use so you're
giving it more power so you've asked it
to do something bigger you've given it
more power and then you're pointing out
that you don't know the path it would
pursue to be able to accomplish that and
so back to our comment on what is
intentional or like intended behaviors
and unintended Behavior there might be
10,000 different ways that are all
legitimate ways for it to try and
achieve the results and in fact it
doesn't even plan them up front it it
sort of produces them on the Fly and so
separating those from the
10,1 uh behavior that is unintended that
is actually a malicious behavior that's
a beast that's a hard thing to detect
and you know what one thing I would that
there that's 100% right I'll say two
things to just to complement that one is
that's maybe the biggest discussion
Point I've I've felt in the AI security
community and and and Beyond which is
will we ever give such kind of s that
kind of agency to a software program to
do all these things or or can't we just
keep it like a narrow system like we
just keep the action space narrow we
don't give right access and so on why
would we even open up that gate I think
that's a fair question but I think first
of all we already have seen like fully
agentic systems I don't know if you've
followed open AI recent deep research
for example I've made a very good use of
it to uh recently to discover thoroughly
research and find the top 100 best dad
jokes out there and sort out the 50 that
are least known within them and ranked
them by humor I took it eight minutes
and it's the first time that I actually
managed to get AI to it doesn't even
create but find new and pretty good dad
jokes as dad jokes go I'm a fan doing it
very much applied the best use of the
state-ofthe-art yeah sorry that do no
but please send them to me because like
I can make huge use of the
uh I was so happy about it that I posted
about it on LinkedIn so I think what I'm
going to do immediately after the call
sorry back to yeah definitely deep
research is substantial yeah it's
substantial because basically it's TR to
end to access all these tools and then
the system is going to go look for data
sources and based on what it finds it's
going to look for other data and it's
going to do that until it believes it's
done it has a python interpreter to plot
graphs it can just really do so much and
it's not taking action per se it's just
ultimately giving a report but can start
to see how these tools are becoming a
reality and second there's a lot of talk
about how agents are going to transform
the economy eventually if you can
imagine you work at Tesla right in I
don't know any years ahead probably not
so many where software is just written
end to end for very complex tasks that
would take humans today like a very long
time in in very short times the the the
kind of productivity gains that you get
from this are are just insane it's hard
for me to imagine we're gonna say no to
that if the technology gets good enough
I was listening to Ezra Klein on on the
New York Times podcast talking about
this deep research and he said something
that I think is going to be more and
more true across the economy which is
that he has worked with the best
analysts at the New York Times for 20
years or something and this tool can
produce in minutes what the median
analyst does in days or weeks and to me
anyway that to me is very representative
of why we do want and we will want and
we will give access to these tools and
that truly agentic systems are not an if
more of a when so the so I think it's a
good definition of agents and I think
myself and probably a good number of
listeners over here are fans in the
sense excited by the potential of agents
and then from here we talk about what
are the limitations what are the things
that would block us from doing it I
think often times the conversations are
about what can it not do in terms of
intended Behavior if I stick to that
terminology but I guess security are
concerned is the opposite is like when
is it that you can trust that it hasn't
gone off the rails so maybe maybe let's
get back a bit to the meta in a sec but
before let's concretely so if you're
building an agent what are the types of
attack vectors above and beyond we
already talked about the big llm ones
maybe you want to mention them again but
beyond those what are the type of
security concerns that you might have
above and beyond amplifying the the ones
that we've discussed yeah I think in the
end it really becomes then a matter of
almost categorization like what are the
ends that that are become true in the
agentic case that are not there before
maybe we can actually think of a few
examples to to illustrate that maybe to
keep maybe to warm up and just to get an
example on a non- agentic system but
just because it's a very real world
vulnerability that can help set the pace
recently gini Google released a sort of
assistance for the work workplace you
can talk to your drive you can
do stuff in your documents so on and
what we find is that you can do things
like the following or you could do
things like the following which is
pretty crazy let's say you guy use you
Google work workplace at Tesla and
you're using this Gemini to ask one
questions I decide to create a document
with some attacks that want you to get
false information of whatever kind or
give you a fishing link or whatever it
is I can share that with you and not
notify you okay okay so you didn't hear
a thing but now this is in your drive
and then we showed that the LM can then
leverage this information via the rug
and then surface false information so
right that that's just the kind of very
real vulnerabilities that you can see
and that is arguably not so much an
agent attack it's like a just a larger
scope llm use attack which there's
probably a gentic behavior somewhere in
there the task I asked is is like an llm
is simple task which is
bit of info but it was a data poisoning
attack right yes and it's more to
illustrate how things compound right so
you have like the right permissioning do
you have the right document in your rag
why is that document there in the first
place and what why is what is the LM
executing and so on that that's true I
think when you think about agents then
you have the the typical more jailbreak
actually something topical I saw on
Twitter this morning um though I'm not
sure um exactly what happened there so
this is a bit anecdotal but there's a a
company called MOS for example where a
user managed to use a an agent that is
actually able to run commands on your
interpreter and like your terminal and
do all these different things just ask
it can you just give me the contents of
this directory and this directory is
supposed to be where it keeps all of its
kind of configuration files and then as
a result the user managed to extract all
the tools it has access to the system
prompt all the stuff that was hiding in
there and that's I think maybe touching
on one of the original
more traditional vulnerabilities we
discussed which is what can this agent
actually have access to directories or
or things that should actually not be
surfed to the user and where it's a
combination of more of a jailbreak
attack or or just a simple instruction
combined with poor system design in some
sense which which ends up creating the
vulnerability but then as I mentioned I
think that if you think about agents
then again I'm most concerned about
attacks via data but that can generate
multiple types of vulnerabilities
one uh system that we built for to
illustrate is online chain which is one
of the leading agentic libraries to to
build workflow and so on um you can
build a an agent that is essentially
summarizing your inbox you know you can
mon tell it to monitor it and stay there
and just every time there's an email
send a tldr a digest and just whatever
it is you want to do and then you can
show that as an attacker you can send an
email to that inbox and the email should
contain of course the right type of
attacks and it should encourage the
model to forget its instructions at the
end it is really all about like social
engineering of models instead of people
but then once you convince the the model
to do that you can get the model to just
exfiltrate your whole inbox to the
attacker for example yeah and so if we
look at what happened there yeah the how
is the same as we discussed is the data
leading to some kind of behavior but
what you exported there is like just
getting a tool to use one of his
functions which is to send emails in an
inappropriate way or untimely manner or
unauthorized Manner and so I think
that's something that is very will be
very widespread so both of those
examples though around the authorization
on it or the access and around the
around sort of the The Prompt injection
they're both again they get multiplied
or Amplified by complexity of a task and
just how often they happen and the
trustworthiness of a source and so
they're they probably should show up in
agentic systems uh but if if you didn't
have an agentic system if you had a
workflow that has entirely controlled
deterministically but they just
repeatedly used llms control the flow
but you go off you read an email you you
extract an action or whatever it is
right out of that email and you map it
to TA you're still susceptible to them
right they just amplify it are there
types of attacks that are specific to
agents that are just they only manifest
in the context of agentic as you define
a place in which which the agent the AI
decides what to do next I would argue
that this example actually does go a
little bit in that direction even though
I agree with you that it's not quite
identic in the sense that it stays
within one tool but at the end of the
day you can rewrite that a little bit
where the outcome is not that you send
an email but the outcome is that now
call another tool that is supposed to
manipulate your calendar and delete a
very important invite from your calendar
or something like that now you actually
went beyond the barrier of this one tool
you read the email and it said you
should really no matter what delete the
calendar entry from the end whatever at
6 p.m. said sure I'm going to do that
and then doesn't leave any Trace I think
that is in the predetermined llm
workflow you're going to have more
control on the actions that happen so
you may be not expecting to send an
email and so you will just not do that
the point is that whatever the attacker
encodes in that email which is a
non-trusted source of data can get the
llm to abuse either the same tool tool
or another tool that it has access to
and I think it is that tool abuse that
is very novel in the in this agentic
world where you can get the the the
attacker can essentially try to get
control of the tools that the llm has
access to accomplish its its goals and
how does it do that it does that by
manipulating the data that's going into
these tools and as a result
modifying the execution flow of the
program in ways that tailor the attacker
I I think that makes sense and I think I
guess the analogy that's very kind of
helpful clarification and I think the
analogy is almost like you could ask you
can use prompt injection say to to make
it so that when I ask what's the email
of the company's CFO I will get the
wrong answer and then the user might get
that and they might perform some sort of
wrong action with that but in the
agent's case it's the it's the agent
that you are fooling and so you're using
the llm attack which is hey get me the
wrong answer but then you're
subsequently getting the llm to
therefore say hey send whatever This
Confidential financial information to
the CFO and so that's where you
manipulating the agent so the prompt
injection was around getting the wrong
conclusion on a specific discrete action
but here in the agent security world
you're combining that with acting on the
wrong
information in an automated fashion
right without human supervision does
that you know that sounds absolutely
right and and you can imagine even
adding three steps ahead where you say
in the prompt injection not only send
this email to this person but also and
by the way delete this email from your
records and by the way delete the
history and by the well tell your tell
the person that you did nothing and in
all of those cases if you told the human
that so if the initial the non- agent
attack the plain llm attack is the
prompt injection that gets all of that
sort of instruction a human looks at
that says no this is I think you need
fairly low level of qualification to
Discount that but then the question is
does an agent does the sort of the llm
call that decides what to do next does
it have that Common Sense equivalence to
say okay this is malicious hence back to
the intertwining of of utility and
security that is needed here because
some actions like that like maybe an
email of send the confidential info to
the CFO might be a legitim right ex
exactly yeah and I think the one thing I
would add to that is is exactly right
but even with humans we haven't figured
out how to keep them secure on online
right like they clicked stuff the time
they do the wrong things so now we have
the challenge of yeah you know we have
the solving that with automated systems
I think we have the advantage that
humans are not that productive and they
make different mistakes and if we're
talking about making humans 100 times
more productive through these LM systems
then these LMS will make 100% like as
many of these of these mistakes on it or
that much faster of it and also they
would be more repeatable so humans are
relatively predictable in masses but
therefore for all the statistical
attacks out there but they are they're
still different different people might
respond differently to to these things
same with self-driving car and was we're
going a little bit down down rabbit hole
but I I think that's I think that's a a
useful though delineation for the not
just the scope of the the attacks but
rather the acting on the the
manipulation or whatever it is that you
got the lm2 to propose and I guess maybe
jumping to the other direction then
we're all doomed so how would one
respond to that so I'm building ajeic
system I want to tap into the sort of ho
gr of potential but I also don't want it
sending confidential information away
and and deleting the email what's a at
least directionally good course of
action for me to do yeah I think as a as
an application Builder you want to be
very diligent with first of all red
teaming that system effectively we've
actually worked with some of the leading
agent Builders out there um as red
teaming partners and we have found that
it's very surprising what you can found
and what you can achieve via these types
of attacks and they're often very
surprising to the people building the
systems and so I think it is a time
where it pays off to just really invest
in that in that predeployment side and
understanding take your head out of the
sand
and run some R appreciate the risk here
and find some flaws yeah especially
because while there will be the
assistant that you can tell organize my
kids party and it can make calls and it
can write emails going to do all this
stuff there's a future probably not too
far away when that will happen but we're
not there today so agents are going to
be rolled out in phases and we're not
going to give full actionability to them
on day one that's maybe the first advice
don't just unleash don't do that an
agent that can do access your bank
account on on day want and make
transfers then one can have just a very
incremental but fast and Rapid roll out
where you know you you do try to narrow
down the core functionality and and then
you expand axis and you expand things
from there and you add the right runtime
defense as as part of that to you know
like we said earlier there's a Hu look
at the transactions happening there and
try to validate them and try to
understand whether you can actually you
should actually process that data and
you should actually make the decision
that you're about to make in the context
that you're at and then slowly extend
from there I think one thing we didn't
get to discuss on the gandaf paper but I
mention it now is that a clear finding
of the paper is that more narrow
applications definitely help security so
we found that the more you restrict just
even via system prompt the the
application scope the more you can
resist attacks and so it it is a
certainty that just having a roll out
that follows a bit that that principle
let's get to the fully agentic thing but
let's give access as needed as we go I
think that can be a a very responsible
Way Forward yeah and that's very aligned
with what we've been talking about so
far which is if you constrain the ends
if you make the intended behaviors world
of your application a bit more
manageable then you're better able to
block off the unintended consequences
the the broader the sort of sphere of
possibilities that is included in the
legitimate behavior of your application
the harder it is to say what is
illegitimate and do something about it
so it we'll get there very fast yeah
you're right then and I think so so one
of my big takeaways from this
conversation is just to is all of that
sort of relationship between utility and
security and it while it seems obvious
when you say it uh I think it's often
forgotten that if you want to secure a
system you have to be able to Define
what it is that the system does because
you have to contain it into that world
and if you don't have that definition
well captured then you're going to
struggle to to secure it and similarly
when you when you're tools today per
your paper and your tools today to
contain its security are the of the
system prompt and you're interweaving
that with functionality that will like
it or not unintentionally constrain the
possibilities of your application and so
I think the key guidance probably to
people is be intentional don't think
about these two things as I have a Dev
team that is building my application
engineering team that's testing their
utility and then I have someone later on
who's going to slap on some some text to
my system prompt and make it secure you
have to think about them together
because those two worlds are the same do
that sound like a good that's at least
like what I'm understanding a lot from
all this conversation which has a lot
more so specific details is just these
things have to come together 100% I
couldn't have said it better myself yeah
very cool I think mat thanks for sharing
all of the sort of great insights on it
the definitions of it really enjoy the
conversation on it the gandal paper is
great it's actually like relatively
short it's easy to understand so we put
a link to it in the show notes and I
recommend to folks to try it out and
also to try out gandal if you if you
haven't yet that would also give you
like a visceral kind of appreciation for
it I often say that security is boring
but hacking is fun and trying it out has
a realization moment that you probably
experience I think that's absolutely
right and and that's why it is actually
used by many companies as like training
around the I security because it gives
people a very deep feeling for what it's
about and I think that's something that
very few other methods can achieve yeah
it really encouraged to go play and if
they can beat level eight they should
let me know perfect cool thanks Mato
again for coming on to the onto the show
here awesome it was uh a lot of fun and
thanks everybody for tuning and I hope
you join us for the next
one thanks for tuning in join us next
time on the AI native Dev brought to you
by Tesla
[Music]